<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes"?><rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom"><channel><title>Ashutosh Singh Rawat</title><link>https://ashutoshsinghrawat.com/</link><description>Recent content on Ashutosh Singh Rawat</description><generator>Hugo</generator><language>en-us</language><lastBuildDate>Sat, 03 Jan 2026 10:00:00 +0530</lastBuildDate><atom:link href="https://ashutoshsinghrawat.com/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml"/><item><title>2025 Was the Last Normal Year for Software Engineers</title><link>https://ashutoshsinghrawat.com/posts/2025-was-the-last-normal-year-for-software-engineers/</link><pubDate>Sat, 03 Jan 2026 10:00:00 +0530</pubDate><guid>https://ashutoshsinghrawat.com/posts/2025-was-the-last-normal-year-for-software-engineers/</guid><description>&lt;p&gt;If you&amp;rsquo;ve been feeling like something &amp;ldquo;snapped&amp;rdquo; in late 2024 and 2025—that your work still looks the same on the surface, but under the hood it&amp;rsquo;s suddenly… different—you&amp;rsquo;re not alone. The tickets, the stand‑ups, the sprints are all still here, but what it &lt;em&gt;means&lt;/em&gt; to be a software engineer is quietly changing in front of us.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I have a strong hunch that when we look back a few years from now, we&amp;rsquo;ll say: 2025 was the last normal year for SWE. Not &amp;ldquo;the year all the jobs vanished,&amp;rdquo; but the last year where it still made sense to think in terms of big IT headcounts, pyramids of junior devs grinding through mundane work, and &amp;ldquo;coding&amp;rdquo; as the primary way individual engineers create value.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Because if AI agents can now take on hours of serious work in one shot—and are on track to handle days or weeks worth of it soon—then a lot of the industry logic we grew up with simply stops making sense.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;hr&gt;
&lt;p&gt;One of the reasons I feel this so strongly is my own experience &amp;ldquo;vibe coding&amp;rdquo; since the end of 2024. At first, it&amp;rsquo;s playful: you toss half‑baked ideas at the model, it spits out working code, and you get this slight guilty rush—like you&amp;rsquo;re cheating on an exam and somehow getting away with it. But very quickly, that feeling changes. You realise that for a &lt;em&gt;huge&lt;/em&gt; chunk of the work that used to occupy junior and mid‑level developers—CRUD boilerplate, glue code, small refactors, tests, migrations—the model isn&amp;rsquo;t just helping you. It&amp;rsquo;s doing the first 70–80% almost completely on its own, and you&amp;rsquo;re mostly editing and steering.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Now, zoom out from one developer to a typical IT services pyramid. For decades, these companies were basically arbitraging human time. Lots of juniors at the bottom, a thinner middle of project managers and tech leads, and a tiny layer at the top that actually understood business value and systems end‑to‑end. The model worked because you needed a ton of human &amp;ldquo;processing power&amp;rdquo; to move requirements to production: manual testing, hand‑rolled integrations, low‑risk features churned out sprint after sprint.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;AI breaks that pyramid in the most boring, inevitable way possible: it chews through the bottom and middle. Not all at once, and not perfectly, but relentlessly.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Another reason 2025 feels like an inflection point is the quantitative side of this story. Benchmarks have quietly shifted from &amp;ldquo;can this model answer trivia and write leetcode solutions?&amp;rdquo; to &amp;ldquo;how many hours of a competent human&amp;rsquo;s work can this system realistically shoulder on a messy, multi‑step task?&amp;rdquo; That&amp;rsquo;s a fundamentally different question. And the answer has gone from &amp;ldquo;minutes&amp;rdquo; to &amp;ldquo;several hours&amp;rdquo; frighteningly fast, with credible people arguing that we&amp;rsquo;re on a curve where those &amp;ldquo;time horizons&amp;rdquo; might double every few months.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;What that means in plain language is: the kind of task that used to keep a junior dev busy for an afternoon—a small feature, a non‑trivial refactor, a migration with some edge cases—is exactly the kind of task that an agent can now take a serious swing at, end‑to‑end, while you go for a walk and come back to review the pull request. Today that still feels magical; in a couple of years, it&amp;rsquo;s going to feel normal.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Now, I know some of you may be thinking: &amp;ldquo;Isn&amp;rsquo;t this just hype? We&amp;rsquo;ve seen automation waves before. Don&amp;rsquo;t these tools always look great in demos and then crumble on real‑world codebases?&amp;rdquo;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;You&amp;rsquo;re right to be skeptical. Anyone who has actually tried to plug an &amp;ldquo;AI agent&amp;rdquo; into a non‑toy repo knows how quickly they can hallucinate, get lost in the file tree, or generate confident nonsense. The key difference this time is that we&amp;rsquo;re not talking about little autocomplete tricks in isolation. We&amp;rsquo;re talking about full workflows where the model can read large swathes of context, plan multi‑step changes, call tools (tests, linters, CI, APIs), and iterate on its own output. The failures are very real—but so is the slope of the curve.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Another objection you might have is: &amp;ldquo;Won&amp;rsquo;t this just create &lt;em&gt;more&lt;/em&gt; demand for engineers? Every productivity increase in tech so far led to &lt;em&gt;more&lt;/em&gt; software, not less.&amp;rdquo;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;That&amp;rsquo;s partly true, and it will stay true for the engineers who adapt. There will absolutely be more software, more experiments, more agents, more systems to design and supervise. But the structure of that demand changes.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Think about the classic outsourcing story: a client has a big backlog of mundane work. A services firm promises to do it cheaper by hiring lots of juniors. Margins are thin, quality is variable, but the model &amp;ldquo;works&amp;rdquo; because you&amp;rsquo;re trading money for human attention at scale. Now imagine the same client in 2028. Do they really need a hundred juniors doing mundane work if ten strong engineers with good agentic tools can deliver the same output—or better—by orchestrating a small army of AI workers? It&amp;rsquo;s hard to see how the old pyramid survives that math.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;So where does that leave you, the individual developer reading this?&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;One of the most important shifts is identity. If you still think of yourself primarily as &amp;ldquo;the person who writes code,&amp;rdquo; you&amp;rsquo;re going to feel this decade as a constant threat. Every new capability will feel like it&amp;rsquo;s eating your lunch. On the other hand, if you start to think of yourself as &amp;ldquo;the person who designs and owns systems of humans &lt;em&gt;and&lt;/em&gt; AI agents to deliver business outcomes,&amp;rdquo; the same curve suddenly looks like your biggest ally.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Instead of panicking every time an agent can do another slice of your work, you start asking:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;How do I scope work so that an agent can own it for a few hours or days?&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;How do I break down a week‑long project into phases that a model can handle, while I only step in at key review checkpoints?&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;How do I wire up my tools, repos, tests, and infra so that agents can do real work safely, not just churn out cute demos?&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;p&gt;At that point, what you&amp;rsquo;re doing day to day is less &amp;ldquo;coding&amp;rdquo; and more &amp;ldquo;directing&amp;rdquo;. You&amp;rsquo;re specifying problems, setting constraints, deciding what &amp;ldquo;good&amp;rdquo; looks like, and then delegating execution to a mix of humans and agents. Your leverage comes from taste, architecture, product sense, and your ability to communicate with these systems—just like a good manager&amp;rsquo;s leverage comes from how they lead people, not how many lines of code they personally write.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Now, I know another fear lurking here is: &amp;ldquo;Does this mean only the &amp;rsquo;top 1%&amp;rsquo; of engineers have a place in the future? What about everyone else who&amp;rsquo;s just… solid?&amp;rdquo;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;All that being said, I&amp;rsquo;m not saying &amp;ldquo;only geniuses survive&amp;rdquo;. What changes is the &lt;em&gt;shape&lt;/em&gt; of &amp;ldquo;solid&amp;rdquo;. Being the person who quietly ships tickets on time but never really owns problems is going to be harder and harder to justify, because a well‑configured agent can look a lot like that person on paper. But being the person who can take a fuzzy business goal, turn it into a clear plan, orchestrate agents and tools to execute most of it, and then refine the result into something users actually love—that&amp;rsquo;s going to be extraordinarily valuable, and not just at FAANG‑style companies.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In fact, one of the more optimistic possibilities here is that individuals and very small teams get &amp;ldquo;agency&amp;rdquo; (pun intended) that used to be reserved for huge organisations. When a solo engineer with good agentic tooling can do the work of a small team, the barrier to trying new things drops. You don&amp;rsquo;t have to beg for headcount to run an experiment; you spin up some agents, point them at your code and data, and supervise. The constraint shifts from &amp;ldquo;how many people can I hire?&amp;rdquo; to &amp;ldquo;how many good ideas and how much taste can I bring to the table?&amp;rdquo;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;At the end of the day, when I say &amp;ldquo;2025 was the last normal year for SWE&amp;rdquo;, I&amp;rsquo;m not saying that 2026 is the year everyone gets fired and the machines take over. I&amp;rsquo;m saying that 2025 will probably look, in hindsight, like the last year where you could reasonably plan a career around the old assumptions: big pyramids of human time, slow linear progression from junior to senior doing mostly similar work with more responsibility, and a clear boundary between &amp;ldquo;tools&amp;rdquo; and &amp;ldquo;teammates&amp;rdquo;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;What&amp;rsquo;s coming next is messier and more interesting: a world where you&amp;rsquo;re expected to work &lt;em&gt;through&lt;/em&gt; agents, not just &lt;em&gt;with&lt;/em&gt; them, where your ability to delegate, specify, and judge becomes as important as your ability to implement. If you lean into that now—if you treat today&amp;rsquo;s &amp;ldquo;vibe coding&amp;rdquo; as the training ground for serious AI delegation—you&amp;rsquo;re not just safe, you&amp;rsquo;re early. And in a world where capabilities are compounding this fast, being early is everything.&lt;/p&gt;</description></item><item><title>Neo Brutalism Will Be Everywhere in 2023</title><link>https://ashutoshsinghrawat.com/posts/neo-brutalism-will-be-everywhere-in-2023/</link><pubDate>Wed, 18 Jan 2023 23:18:53 +0530</pubDate><guid>https://ashutoshsinghrawat.com/posts/neo-brutalism-will-be-everywhere-in-2023/</guid><description>&lt;p&gt;Hey there web designers! Are you tired of seeing the same minimalist, clean designs everywhere you look? Well, get ready for a change because I believe that neo-brutalism is going to be everywhere in 2023.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;But wait, you might be thinking, &amp;ldquo;Neo-brutalism? Isn&amp;rsquo;t that the rough, raw, and unrefined architectural style from the 1950s and 60s?&amp;rdquo; And you&amp;rsquo;re right, that is the original definition of brutalism. But in the world of web design, neo-brutalism refers to a style that embraces raw, unpolished elements like bold typography, rough textures, and limited color palettes.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;One of the reasons I believe we&amp;rsquo;ll be seeing more neo-brutalism in 2023 is the rise of nostalgia in design. As we move further into the digital age, there&amp;rsquo;s a growing desire to reconnect with the past and to embrace the tactile and imperfect. Neo-brutalism taps into this nostalgia by harkening back to a time when design was less about perfection and more about raw expression.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Another reason is the desire for authenticity in design. In a world where everything is curated and filtered, people are craving designs that feel real and genuine. Neo-brutalism embraces this authenticity by embracing the imperfections and embracing the roughness of the design. It&amp;rsquo;s a style that doesn&amp;rsquo;t try to hide its flaws, but instead embraces them as part of its charm.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;But let&amp;rsquo;s not forget about the practical side of things. Neo-brutalism is a style that is easy to replicate and highly customizable. It&amp;rsquo;s a style that can be adapted to a wide range of designs and can be used in a variety of ways, from bold and powerful to simple and understated.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Now, I know that some of you might be thinking, &amp;ldquo;But what about accessibility? Won&amp;rsquo;t neo-brutalism make it harder for people with disabilities to use my website?&amp;rdquo; And you&amp;rsquo;re right, it&amp;rsquo;s important to consider accessibility in all of our designs. But neo-brutalism doesn&amp;rsquo;t have to be inaccessible. By choosing appropriate color contrasts and typography, and ensuring that all functionality is still operable via keyboard, we can create neo-brutalist designs that are accessible to all users.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;All that being said, I&amp;rsquo;m not saying that every website in 2023 will be neo-brutalist, but I do believe that we&amp;rsquo;ll start to see more and more of it. Neo-brutalism is a style that taps into our nostalgia and desire for authenticity, and it&amp;rsquo;s a style that is easy to replicate and highly customizable. So, let&amp;rsquo;s embrace the imperfections and the raw elements, and see how we can incorporate neo-brutalism into our designs in 2023.&lt;/p&gt;</description></item><item><title>Ssr Should Be Default</title><link>https://ashutoshsinghrawat.com/posts/ssr-should-be-default/</link><pubDate>Wed, 18 Jan 2023 23:08:25 +0530</pubDate><guid>https://ashutoshsinghrawat.com/posts/ssr-should-be-default/</guid><description>&lt;p&gt;Hey there fellow developers! If you&amp;rsquo;re like me, you&amp;rsquo;re always on the lookout for the latest and greatest technologies and trends in web development. And one trend that I&amp;rsquo;ve been seeing more and more of lately (well, a few years now..) is the use of server-side rendering (SSR) for web applications.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Now, I know that some of you may be thinking, &amp;ldquo;But wait, I&amp;rsquo;ve been using single-page applications (SPAs) for years and they&amp;rsquo;ve worked just fine!&amp;rdquo; And you&amp;rsquo;re right, SPAs have been a popular choice for web development for a while now. But as technology and user needs have evolved, I think it&amp;rsquo;s time for us to start thinking about SSR as the default for web applications.&lt;/p&gt;</description></item><item><title>Are Single Page applications dead?</title><link>https://ashutoshsinghrawat.com/posts/are-single-page-applications-dead/</link><pubDate>Wed, 18 Jan 2023 22:59:34 +0530</pubDate><guid>https://ashutoshsinghrawat.com/posts/are-single-page-applications-dead/</guid><description>&lt;p&gt;Single page applications, or SPAs, have been a popular choice for web development for several years. However, as technology and user needs have evolved, the death of SPAs has been predicted by some in the industry.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;One of the main reasons for this prediction is the rise of mobile devices and the need for faster loading times. SPAs rely on JavaScript to load and render content, which can be slow and clunky on mobile devices with limited processing power. Additionally, Google and other search engines have had difficulty indexing the content on SPAs, making it difficult for users to find them through search.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Another reason for the decline of SPAs is the emergence of new technologies such as Progressive Web Apps (PWAs) and server-side rendering (SSR). PWAs are web applications that can be installed on a user&amp;rsquo;s device and work offline, providing a similar experience to native mobile apps. SSR allows for the rendering of web pages on the server, reducing the load on the client&amp;rsquo;s device and improving the performance of web pages.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Additionally, SPAs can also be difficult to maintain and update, since all the code is bundled into one large JavaScript file. This makes it harder to identify and fix bugs, and can also lead to longer development times.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;All that being said, Single Page Applications are not dead. They are still widely used, and they can be useful in certain cases, such as when building a web application that requires a lot of client-side logic or when you need a fast and responsive user interface.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;However, it&amp;rsquo;s also important to keep in mind that SPAs are not the best solution for all use cases. For example, if you&amp;rsquo;re building a content-heavy website, it may be more beneficial to use traditional server-side rendering to improve search engine optimization and reduce the load on the client&amp;rsquo;s device.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In conclusion, it&amp;rsquo;s important for developers to evaluate the specific needs of their project and choose the appropriate technology for the job. While SPAs have been a popular choice for web development in the past, the rise of new technologies and changing user needs mean that they may not be the best option for every project. It&amp;rsquo;s important to stay aware of the latest developments in web development and to choose the solution that best meets the needs of your project.&lt;/p&gt;</description></item><item><title>Imagining The Future</title><link>https://ashutoshsinghrawat.com/posts/imagining-the-future/</link><pubDate>Thu, 11 Feb 2016 10:00:00 +0530</pubDate><guid>https://ashutoshsinghrawat.com/posts/imagining-the-future/</guid><description>&lt;p&gt;Views on how consumer technology will change in the near future.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Change in technology is not new. Every couple of years, we see something new in technology that improves on something already cherished. Every couple of decades or so, we see technology changing as a whole. Those of you who know about the Koomey&amp;rsquo;s or Moore&amp;rsquo;s Law and Intel&amp;rsquo;s Tic and Tock know what I&amp;rsquo;m talking about. In the five years since, I have had the pleasure to use many mobile operating systems, command Google Glass to take pictures for me, instruct Leap Motion (à la Minority Report), look like an idiot enjoying a VR Headset, fly/crash a Quadcopter (I own one, still cant figure out how to fly that thing), track my health with a fitness tracker, or read Malcolm Gladwell on an E book Reader.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Just because technology is there, doesn&amp;rsquo;t mean it is for everyone (Big Data); doesn&amp;rsquo;t mean it has matured (VR); and definitely doesn&amp;rsquo;t mean that it is always useful (Smart Appliances/Bad IoT, 3D TV&amp;rsquo;s). As a person with lackluster memory (a consumer), I thank my Smartphone for remembering the phone number of my 20th best friend so that I can grant him a customary birthday greeting once a year. Even though I consider myself satisfactorily techie, a smartphone and a laptop is all I need to continue with my work and personal other worldly pleasures. For me, no tablet can provide me the convenience of calling, SMS, messaging, and casual Facebook/YouTube surfing in a pocket-sized device that my smartphone can. No smartwatch or fitness tracker currently in market can replace my no-fuss Seiko watch that is ready to show date and time and bear the optimum weight on my wrist for years at stretch, without a recharge.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In the last five years of my gadget self discovery, I&amp;rsquo;ve experienced many patterns that I think, will hold true in the future. What will my gadget future look like? If you are anything like me, chances are it will be the same for you too.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Previce — Primary Device.&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;While enjoying the morning sun, I savor the perfect Chai and read headlines that will get me ready for the day. My job requires me to be updated on the current trends in technology and I don&amp;rsquo;t like being distracted with news and articles throughout the day. My Previce, now resized to a comfortable 10″ size for reading, knows that. It carefully curates, prioritizes, and summarizes just the right amount of news I&amp;rsquo;d read in the leisure time I have before I begin my fitness regime. My Previce is perfect. It knows all my preferences and makes sure I get the right user experience from the world around me.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I begin my fitness regime with some yoga exercises. Previce selects the type of exercises I do based on my latest body vitals and coaches me through the training while all along tracking my vitals. In its 5″ form, tied to my armband, it can track all the vitals it needs. In the last month, it has recommended yoga, strength training, and endurance training based on my vitals and health goals set by my physician. Previce is clever. It also communicates with the Previce of my doctor, spouse, co-workers, and friends and keeps us all connected.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Now ready to leave for the office, my Previce communicates with my car and sends my destination in advance. I must clarify its not my car, it is an autonomous service to which I have subscribed. The car automatically comes in front of my house just before I am ready to leave for the office. It drives me to the office while I read emails from work. After dropping me off, it goes to pick up another person who has subscribed to the service.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;My inbox, crazier than ever, is easier to manage. Previce has changed it for the better. It automatically segregates the spam, fills forms, accepts meeting requests, marks emails as read, and manages my calendar to make sure I only read the emails meant for me. By communicating with all my co-worker&amp;rsquo;s Previces and the different services, it books conference rooms and can also make restaurant reservations on my behalf.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Previce is a powerful device now that it is connected to my 24″ display glass with motion sensing, video, and J.A.R.V.I.S (à la Iron Man) like AI audio inputs commands. On my desk, where I work on anything from casual internet research, and creating presentations to photo editing, and video creation — it can wirelessly utilize parallel computing to provide me the computing power I need, on-demand. Everything is in the cloud so I can take my work with me wherever necessary.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;As I wrap up my workday before I meet my family for the dinner reservation that my Previce suggested, I wonder how easy, efficient, simple and yet somewhat eerie my life is with Previce at the helm.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Can Previce Be Real?&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;For all intents and purposes, Previce is real. Technology existing in 2016 allows us to create such a device. As previously stated, great consumer technology is not necessary a result of an invention but innovation in piecing the right inventions together and providing it with a lucrative businesses model. Previce is an imagination of a personal gadget that is less about technology and more about utility, user experience, and coherent technology solutions that work well together. If brought to reality, it would do a more than I can imagine or write. If I were to play an oracle, in the next five years, the smartphone will evolve to become a Previce-like device. As different industries evolve with technology, apps and smartphones will create an ecosystem capable enough to create the future I imagine for myself.&lt;/p&gt;</description></item></channel></rss>